<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[The Open Network Geek Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://opennetgeek.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://opennetgeek.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-05-18T19:29:21-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://opennetgeek.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Diego Dompe]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using OpenSwitch Appliance With GNS3]]></title>
    <link href="http://opennetgeek.github.io/blog/2016/04/20/using-openswitch-appliance-with-gns3/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-20T18:52:32-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://opennetgeek.github.io/blog/2016/04/20/using-openswitch-appliance-with-gns3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center no-border" src="http://opennetgeek.github.io/images/openswitchstencilbig1.png"></p>

<p><strong>Note</strong>: This article was <a href="https://opennetgeek.wordpress.com/2016/04/20/using-openswitch-appliance-with-gns3/">originally published here</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong>This post has been updated to account for some recent changes
in the appliance configuration (support for up to 7 front ports). In
my <a href="http://opennetgeek.github.io/blog/2016/04/19/developing-openswitch-with-linux-vm-slash-os-x-host/">previous
post</a> I
described my developer setup to work with OpenSwitch. At the end of my
post I showed how to download the build system, and configure and build
an &lsquo;appliance&rsquo; image.</p>

<h2>What Is An OpenSwitch Appliance?</h2>

<p>The appliance is a virtual machine image (in OVA format) that could be
run on VirtualBox or VMware (on this articule I will focus on
VirtualBox) and provides a software datapath (based in OVS right now,
but P4 support it&rsquo;s landing soon). All the rest of the OpenSwitch stack
is the same that you will see in a real hardware, and obviously the
software datapath has certain limitations and features not implemented.</p>

<p>Despite his limitations, the appliance is a really nice way to get your
hands into OpenSwitch without having real hardware.</p>

<p>If you are using the development environment, you can find the appliance .ova file on the
images directory after completing the build, but otherwise you can also
download a periodic image from the <a href="https://archive.openswitch.net/artifacts/periodic/master/latest/appliance/">project
archives</a> (keep
in mind this is a developer snapshot, so things may be broken or
uncomplete sometimes).</p>

<p>The Appliance has currently <del>4</del> <a href="https://review.openswitch.net/#/c/7859/">8</a>
network ports (this is the max number of interfaces supported by VirtualBox): eth0 to eth7. The
port &lsquo;eth0&rsquo; will be the management port, and the other ones are &lsquo;front
ports&rsquo;.</p>

<h2>How To Use The Appliance?</h2>

<!--more-->


<p>The first good use for the appliance is that you can import it into
VirtualBox, and by using &lsquo;bridged&rsquo; interface with a dedicated NIC (for
example an USB ethernet dongle), you can make the appliance talk with a
real piece of hardware, like a traditional router. This allows you to
play with LLDP, BGP, OSPF, etc. I won&rsquo;t go into details of a setup like
this for this article, and is left as exercise to the reader.</p>

<p>In the previous scenario, using one Appliance was nice, but how about using
multiple appliances together? Like creating a virtual CLOS? For that we
will be using GNS3.</p>

<p>If you never heard of <a href="https://www.gns3.com">GNS3</a> before, is an Open Source platform to
create virtual networks and deployments inside your laptop, with some
nice UI. Even more useful, it&rsquo;s cross platform. I will be focusing my
demo here on using it over Mac, but should be easy to extrapolate if you
are a Windows user.</p>

<h2>Setup OpenSwitch Appliance On VirtualBox for GNS3</h2>

<p>In order to use the appliance with GNS3, you need to import the OVA file
into VirtualBox (File -> Import Appliance). The OVA generated by
OpenSwitch is compatible out of the box with GNS3 since April 26th 2016.</p>

<h3><a name="install_and_configure">Installing And Configuring GNS3</a></h3>

<p>First, <a href="https://www.gns3.com/software/download">download GNS3</a> from
their project page and install it (yes, you have to register). Next, I
recommend that you <a href="https://www.wireshark.org/download.html">install
Wireshark</a> to have the
capabilities of snooping on the traffic of the virtual network.</p>

<p>On recent OS X, when trying to run the GNS3 application you may get an
error message:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>“GNS3” is damaged and can’t be opened</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This is a wrong error message, and the problem is really that you need
to reduce the security of the system to allow executing applications
that are not from the App Store. You can change this setting on: System
Preferences -> Security &amp; Privacy -> Allow apps download from:
Anywhere.</p>

<p>When you first start GNS3, it will start the Setup Wizard, and
ask for a server. Select the &lsquo;Local server&rsquo;. We would not need the GNS3
VM for running the OpenSwitch appliance, since will be run on top of
VirtualBox.</p>

<p><img class="center no-border" src="http://opennetgeek.github.io/images/gns3-setup-1.png"></p>

<p>On the next window select to &lsquo;Add a VirtualBox virtual machine&rsquo; (at this
point you should have already imported the OpenSwitch Appliance into
VirtualBox for this to work).</p>

<p><img class="center no-border" src="http://opennetgeek.github.io/images/gns3-setup-2.png"></p>

<p>Next, select the OpenSwitch Appliance Image that was imported into
VirtualBox, and enable &ldquo;Use as linked base VM&rdquo;.</p>

<p><img class="center no-border" src="http://opennetgeek.github.io/images/ops-setup-1.png"></p>

<p>After of click on &lsquo;Finish&rsquo;, the preference panel for VirtualBox VMs will
show and you will have to edit the recently created template to add some
custom configuration: On the &lsquo;General Settings&rsquo; tab:</p>

<ul>
<li>Template Name: <em>OpenSwitch</em></li>
<li>Default name format: <em>{name}-{0}</em></li>
<li>Symbol: <em>/local/path/to/<a href="https://archive.openswitch.net/logo/OpenSwitchStencil.png">OpenSwitchStencil.png</a></em></li>
<li>Category: <em>Switches</em></li>
<li>RAM: <em>512 MB</em></li>
<li>☑︎ Enable remote console</li>
<li>☐ Enable ACPI shutdown</li>
<li>☑︎ Start VM in headless mode</li>
<li>☑︎ Use as a linked base VM</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="center no-border" src="http://opennetgeek.github.io/images/ops-setup-2.png"></p>

<p>On the &lsquo;Network&rsquo; tab:</p>

<ul>
<li>Adapters: <em>8</em></li>
<li>First port name: <em>mgmt</em></li>
<li>Name format: <em>eth{port1}</em></li>
<li>Segment size: <em>0</em></li>
<li>Type: <em>PCNet-FAST III (Am79c973)</em></li>
<li>☑︎ Allow GNS3 to use any configured VirtualBox adapter</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="center no-border" src="http://opennetgeek.github.io/images/ops-setup-3.png"></p>

<h2>Creating A Simple Connection Between Two Appliance Instances</h2>

<p>Now, it&rsquo;s time to deploy two instances and verify connectivity between
them:</p>

<ul>
<li>Create a new project and save it (the linked VM won&rsquo;t work on
temporal projects).</li>
<li>Click on the &lsquo;Browse all devices&rsquo; button on the left panel to show
the available devices, then drag two OpenSwitch instances into the
canvas (you can see in your VirtualBox UI that two new virtual
machines are created).</li>
<li>Use the &lsquo;Add link&rsquo; tool from the left panel (the one that looks like
a cable with an RJ45 plug) to connect the two instances over the
eth1 port of both.</li>
</ul>


<p>At the end of this setup your project should look like this:</p>

<p><img class="center no-border" src="http://opennetgeek.github.io/images/project-1.png"></p>

<p>Before starting the simulation, I will attach wireshark to one of the
interfaces to see the packets between the machines:</p>

<ul>
<li>Right click on one of side of the links and select &lsquo;Start capture&rsquo;.
This will create a pipe that will output the contents into a pcap
file that wireshark can feed from. This can only be done when the
link is down, so you need to start the captures before turning on
the VM.</li>
</ul>


<p>Now you can start your machines by hitting the top &lsquo;Play&rsquo; button. This
will start both VMs. Then you can double click on both machines and a
Terminal will open where you get access to the serial console of the
machine. You can login with the user and password &lsquo;netop&rsquo; (this will
enter into the traditional CLI mode, but you can also login as root into
a bash shell):</p>

<p><img class="center no-border" src="http://opennetgeek.github.io/images/console-1.png"></p>

<p>At this point you can right click on the link where we are capturing the
traffic, and select &lsquo;Start Wireshark&rsquo;. This will open a WireShark window
that is feeding from the pcap capture of the traffic from the port.</p>

<p><strong>Note</strong>: There is currently an open
<a href="https://tree.taiga.io/project/openswitch/issue/840">bug</a> in OpenSwitch
where the image may fail to boot properly the data path. To validate
your appliance booted properly run the following command:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'># show interface eth1</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If the reported MAC address is (null), then reboot the appliance and
check again. I will update this blog as soon as the bug is closed.</p>

<p>Now is time to see some traffic flowing between the machines: let&rsquo;s enable
LLDP on both ports, and we should be able to see both switches
identifying each other, and the traffic flowing thru Wireshark. Let&rsquo;s
issue the following commands on the CLI of both switches:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>switch# config
</span><span class='line'>switch(config)# interface eth1
</span><span class='line'>switch(config-if)# no shutdown
</span><span class='line'>switch(config-if)# exit
</span><span class='line'>switch(config)# lldp enable
</span><span class='line'>switch(config)# exit</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>After these commands are entered on both switches, we can now show the
LLDP neighbor information on any of the switches:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>switch# show lldp neighbor-info eth1
</span><span class='line'>Port                           : eth1
</span><span class='line'>Neighbor entries               : 1
</span><span class='line'>Neighbor entries deleted       : 0
</span><span class='line'>Neighbor entries dropped       : 0
</span><span class='line'>Neighbor entries age-out       : 0
</span><span class='line'>Neighbor Chassis-Name          : switch
</span><span class='line'>Neighbor Chassis-Description   : OpenSwitch 0.3.0 (dill) Linux 3.14.19-yocto-standard #1 SMP PREEMPT Wed Mar 23 00:06:21 UTC 2016 x86_64
</span><span class='line'>Neighbor Chassis-ID            : a2:69:35:48:7b:4d
</span><span class='line'>Neighbor Management-Address    : 
</span><span class='line'>Chassis Capabilities Available : Bridge, Router
</span><span class='line'>Chassis Capabilities Enabled   : Bridge, Router
</span><span class='line'>Neighbor Port-ID               : eth1
</span><span class='line'>TTL                            : 120</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And you can see the LLDP advertisements going thru with Wireshark:</p>

<p><img class="center no-border" src="http://opennetgeek.github.io/images/wireshark.png"></p>

<h2>Conclusions And Next Steps</h2>

<p>That is all the fun that we will have for today, hope you find the
information useful. I&rsquo;m planing to blog soon about the following
subjects:</p>

<ul>
<li>A GNS3 setup of a CLOS network, and pushing the configuration using
Ansible (yay!).</li>
<li>Playing with an appliance using P4.</li>
</ul>


<p>Stay tuned!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Developing OpenSwitch With Linux VM/OS X Host]]></title>
    <link href="http://opennetgeek.github.io/blog/2016/04/19/developing-openswitch-with-linux-vm-slash-os-x-host/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-19T14:58:23-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://opennetgeek.github.io/blog/2016/04/19/developing-openswitch-with-linux-vm-slash-os-x-host</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://opennetgeek.github.io/images/ops-mac.jpg" title="OpenSwitch on Mac" alt="OpenSwitch on Mac"></p>

<p><strong>Note</strong>: This article was <a href="https://opennetgeek.wordpress.com/2016/04/19/developing-openswitch-with-linux-vmos-x-host/">originally published here</a>.</p>

<p>One of the purposes when we designed the build system in OpenSwitch, was to make it possible to develop on as many environments as possible. If you have some background with developing networking firmware, the typical developer love to have this VM where everything works perfectly, but makes it impossible to work in your laptop at 30000 feet. This is not really a sin (as long as you can have the VM hosted in your machine), but the problem is that usually is some IT team on charge of the VMs setup, and the deployment is not handled by some automated/version-controlled code.</p>

<p>So for OpenSwitch, we aimed to at least document the requirements and steps for manual setup of your environment. You can read <a href="http://www.openswitch.net/documents/dev/linux-setup">this page</a> to get your Linux machine to ready it for OpenSwitch development.</p>

<p>So, why to write an article about my particular setup? Well, I&rsquo;m a Mac user, so in this article I&rsquo;m going to detail my setup using a OS X host with a Linux VM. This provides some nice tricks that makes your workflow easier if you are using a similar setup. I will also explain the rationale of the setup.</p>

<p>My use of Linux VM for development is mostly thru the Linux CLI and I use NFS to share files between my Mac and Linux. This allows me to use any graphical tool from the Linux VM if I have to, but also to use tools from the host without major hurdles.Read more&hellip;</p>

<h2>Setup the VM</h2>

<!--more-->


<p>The first step is that I will use <a href="https://www.virtualbox.org/">VirtualBox</a> to deploy my Linux VM. You can use any software that you want, but VirtualBox is free and available to any developer, so it&rsquo;s a good target.</p>

<p>Since I&rsquo;m using a Macbook Pro Retina with a i7, I will use the following setup:</p>

<ul>
<li>6 Cores: the Yocto build system can take advantage of the multicore environment, so the more cores, the faster builds. This leaves 2 cores idle for my Mac, so performance doesn&rsquo;t suffer.</li>
<li>4Gb of RAM: A full from-scratch build of the compiler (rare, since we use Yocto&rsquo;s shared states) can consume quite a bit of RAM.</li>
<li>20GB of disk: the build directories from Yocto could be big, averaging 6G each, but the figure could easily go up depending on what you are doing. So having some disk space to spare is a good measure (I personally ran with 160GB)</li>
<li>Two network interfaces:

<ul>
<li>First one will be NAT, so that I can reach the internet independent of the network connection on my Mac (sometimes I use wireless, sometimes I use a thunderbolt dock station).</li>
<li>Second one will be host-only adapter, this provides a internal network so that we can easily communicate between the VM and the host. Using multicast DNS (aka Bonjour), we won' even have to worry about IP addresses on this network.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>For this VM, I will be using <a href="http://mirror.uoregon.edu/ubuntu-releases/14.04.4/ubuntu-14.04.4-server-amd64.iso">Ubuntu LTS 14.04 Server ISO</a>. Right now OpenSwitch works best with this version of Ubuntu (and provides faster build times). We hope to update to the new LTS soon and once we do, I will update this post to reflect that. <strong>Update</strong>: I have added comments about how to make it work with <a href="http://releases.ubuntu.com/16.04/ubuntu-16.04-server-amd64.iso">Ubuntu 16.04</a>!.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m assuming you are familiar with installing an Ubuntu ISO into a VM and will omit those details. The only important detail from the installation would be to install the SSH server. I would recommend that you setup your user account with the same user id that you have in GitHub (this is a good moment to create one, if you don&rsquo;t). Using the same user account makes life easier with gerrit, but is not an strict requirement.</p>

<h2>Proxy Setup</h2>

<p>If you are behind a corporate firewall, be sure to setup your corporate proxies in your user environment:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>cat &lt;&lt;EOF &gt;&gt;~/.profile
</span><span class='line'>export http_proxy=http://your.proxy.com:port
</span><span class='line'>export https_proxy=http://your.proxy.com:port
</span><span class='line'>EOF
</span><span class='line'>source ~/.profile</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If my case, I may be roaming between the office and home, so sometimes I don&rsquo;t use a proxy, in which case I find easy to unset the variables and be able to work. So, I don&rsquo;t like to wire the apt configuration with the proxy as <a href="http://askubuntu.com/questions/257290/configure-proxy-for-apt">explained here</a>, instead I like to run the apt-get command with &lsquo;sudo -E&rsquo; parameter so that it inherits my environment variables and uses the proxy if I have it defined.</p>

<h2>Initial Setup</h2>

<p>First, I usually disable asking password for my user:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>sudo visudo -f /etc/sudoers.d/passwordless-user</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Then enter a line like the following (replace your username):</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>username ALL=(ALL) NOPASSWD:ALL</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Next, let&rsquo;s update the apt package cache:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>sudo apt-get update</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Networking Setup</h2>

<p>The initial installation will configure the machine out of the box to have DHCP on the first network interface, so we will need to add the second interface for automatic startup. So I will add the following lines to /etc/network/interfaces:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>auto eth1
</span><span class='line'>iface eth1 inet dhcp</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Then, bring the interface up:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>sudo ifup eth1</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p><strong>Update</strong>: if you are using 16.04, the network interfaces have different names (to understand why and revert it if you want, take a look here). Run &lsquo;ifconfig -a&rsquo; to find the name of your interfaces.</p>

<p>Next, proceed to install some extra packages and configurations that make networking work better.</p>

<p>dnsmasq: the build system fetches constantly from the servers in order to use the shared states to speed the build. So using a local DNS cache will help reduce the pressure on your DNS (and may save you from raising flags about the high rate of request your machine will be doing).</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>sudo apt-get install dnsmasq</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p><strong>Update</strong>: if you are using 16.04, dnsmasq won&rsquo;t work out of the box since it conflicts with the dnsmasq used by the LXC container daemon. I worked around by disabling LXC (but maybe that solution doesn&rsquo;t work for you):</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>sudo systemctl stop lxc lxc-net
</span><span class='line'>sudo systemctl disable lxc lxc-net</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>nss-mdns: this is the name service resolution to use multicast DNS. This allows the Linux machine to resolve (and as side effect of dependencies, advertise) .local addresses and makes communication with the Mac simpler.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>sudo apt-get install libnss-mdns</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>After this is installed, you should be able to reach your machine with the .local name. Lets say your Linux machine is named linuxvm, then you should be able to run from your Mac:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>ping linuxvm.local</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Headless VM</h2>

<p>After the initial networking setup is ready, I like to run the VM in headless mode from the OS X terminal. To do that, I shutdown the VM from the VirtualBox UI and close the application. Then from an OS X Terminal I can start the VM in the background with (replace the LinuxVM name with the name of your VM:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>VBoxHeadless --startvm LinuxVM --vrde off &</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This will run on the background and as long as you don&rsquo;t close the terminal, the VM will run. Next, I usually connect to the VM from the terminal with (using the mDNS .local resolution):</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>ssh -Y username@linuxvm.local</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The -Y automatically exports X11 apps into my Mac XQuartz, in case you want to use some graphical program from Linux.</p>

<h2>OpenSwitch Development Environment Tweaks</h2>

<p>Create a workspace directory on /ws. This is just an standard I follow  of putting all my work on a separate directory. Makes easier to fine-control the NFS exports from my Linux machine into my Mac host.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>sudo mkdir /ws
</span><span class='line'>sudo chown $USER /ws</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>NFS Server Share Setup</h3>

<p>Installing an NFS server with the proper parameters to allow easy sharing of files between the host an the Mac took me several hours of research. Here is the recipe for it.</p>

<p>Install the NFS server daemon:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>sudo apt-get install nfs-kernel-server</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Configure the /etc/exports file with the following line to allow your Mac host to access the files under /ws with the same user permissions as your Linux user (assuming your user ID is 1000, you can find that with the &lsquo;id&rsquo; command).</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>/ws 192.168.56.1(rw,all_squash,anonuid=1000,anongid=1000,sync,no_subtree_check,insecure)</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Start the NFS server:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>sudo service nfs-kernel-server start</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p><strong>Update</strong>: if you are using 16.04 use systemctl instead of service, and the service is called nfs-server:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>sudo systemctl start nfs-server</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>At this point you should be able to mount the NFS directory from your Mac, by going to the Finder Menu Go  -> Connect to Server&hellip; (or using the ⌘k shortcut). On the server address box enter:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>nfs://yourmachine.local/ws</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>That should get your Mac access over NFS to the directory  /ws and will have the right permission mapping so that files could be changed either from the Linux or Mac environment without permissions conflicts.</p>

<h3>Install Docker</h3>

<p>We are going to be using docker, so we need to install it following the instructions <a href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/installation/linux/ubuntulinux/">here</a>.</p>

<p>If you are using a proxy, you need to setup it up for the docker daemon on /etc/default/docker:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>export http_proxy=http://your.proxy.com:port
</span><span class='line'>export https_proxy=http://your.proxy.com:port</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Then, restart your docker to make the changes take effect:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>sudo service docker restart</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>Prepare for  OpenSwitch Build Environment</h3>

<p>Install the minimal required packages for OpenSwitch development:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>sudo apt-get install gawk wget git-core diffstat unzip texinfo gcc-multilib build-essential chrpath screen curl device-tree-compiler git-review</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>OpenSwitch leverages Yocto&rsquo;s shared-state system, so we want to have a global shared state directory that is shared across all the development environments to speed build time. The OpenSwitch build system will get this information automatically from a variable environment, so I will put it on my profile by default:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>sudo mkdir /ws/openswitch-sstate-cache /ws/openswitch-downloads
</span><span class='line'>sudo chown $USER /ws/openswitch-sstate-cache /ws/openswitch-downloads
</span><span class='line'>echo -e "export SSTATE_DIR=/ws/openswitch-sstate-cache\nexport DL_DIR=/ws/openswitch-downloads" &gt;&gt; ~/.profile
</span><span class='line'>source ~/.profile</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Git And Gerrit Setup</h2>

<p>Setup some initial git setup for working with <a href="https://review.openswitch.net/">OpenSwitch Gerrit</a>. You will need a GitHub account in order to login into gerrit, so I will assume you already have one, and you know how to upload your ssh key into gerrit. You will also need to sign a <a href="http://elinux.org/Developer_Certificate_Of_Origin">DCO</a> when signing for Gerrit, otherwise won&rsquo;t be able to upload code for review (if you are going to contribute as part of your job, you need to follow the steps on the OpenSwitch page to get your employer to sing a corporate contribution agreement).</p>

<p>First, setup git (I like to use colors, and use st as an alias for status):</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>git config --global user.name "John Doe"
</span><span class='line'>git config --global user.email johndoe@example.com
</span><span class='line'>git config --global alias.st status
</span><span class='line'>git config --global color.ui auto</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If you are working behind a corporate firewall, it may be that gerrit ports (29418) are blocked. You can test a telnet connection into the port to confirm if you are blocked. A workaround this restriction is to install socat and use a proxy for the ssh connection:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>sudo apt-get install socat
</span><span class='line'>cat &lt;&lt;EOF &gt;&gt;~/.ssh/config
</span><span class='line'>Host review.openswitch.net
</span><span class='line'>    IdentityFile ~/.ssh/id_rsa
</span><span class='line'>    ProxyCommand socat - PROXY:your.proxy.com:%h:%p,proxyport=&lt;port&gt;
</span><span class='line'>EOF</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If your github username is different from the username in your machine, you may want to configure git to use the right username when doing git reviews:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>git config --global gitreview.username &lt;username&gt;</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>You can verify your connection to gerrit works by issuing this command and getting a similar output:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>ssh -p 29418 &lt;username&gt;@review.openswitch.net
</span><span class='line'>  ****    Welcome to Gerrit Code Review    ****
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  Hi John Doe, you have successfully connected over SSH.
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  Unfortunately, interactive shells are disabled.
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  To clone a hosted Git repository, use:
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  git clone ssh://&lt;username&gt;@review.openswitch.net:29418/REPOSITORY_NAME.git
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>Connection to review.openswitch.net closed.</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Building OpenSwitch</h2>

<p>Finally, I&rsquo;m going to clone the OpenSwitch build system, and build an appliance image that I would use in my next post about working OpenSwitch with GNS3.</p>

<p>First I clone the build system:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>git clone https://git.openswitch.net/openswitch/ops-build ops-appliance
</span><span class='line'>cd ops-appliance
</span><span class='line'>make configure appliance
</span><span class='line'>make</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Now you can sit a wait for the build to complete. If you have a fast internet connection it will take in the order of 15 minutes to download all the caches and sources to build a full OpenSwitch Virtual Appliance. In  my next post we will be using that.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I hope the information is useful. Drop me a comment if you think there is any improvement I can do to the environment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Starting a Blog on Open Software/Hardware + Networking]]></title>
    <link href="http://opennetgeek.github.io/blog/2016/03/22/starting-a-blog-on-open-software-slash-hardware-plus-networking/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-22T14:51:39-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://opennetgeek.github.io/blog/2016/03/22/starting-a-blog-on-open-software-slash-hardware-plus-networking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I’m jumping into water to start writing about some area where I have some
half-decent background: the intersection of Open Software/Hardware and Networking.</p>

<h2>Why?</h2>

<p>You see, I’m a software guy. The pragmatical Linux/OpenSource fanboy kind. What
that means? I have a formal degree on Computer Science, and wrote Linux drivers
and software for embedded systems for 8 years. But I’m also a pragmatical guy:
I know how to write kernel drivers, but I use a Mac laptop every day because
I like things to work. For the last 4 years I have been learning a big from
networking at Hewlett Packard Enterprise, where I have worked on networking
(SDN, ASICs), and more recently on the OpenSwitch project.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Why start writing about the intersection of Open and Networking? These are
interesting times in the networking world: disaggregation, open source,
open hardware, etc. All of this is pretty new for the networking world, and is
specially different because in the old good days you will have limited
information about the technical details of what is going on behind scenes on
your network. Now sharing the knowledge is critical. I have been inspired by
reading blog entries from many in the networking community, and I’m by no
means close to have the expertise of guys like Ivan or Greg, but I think I can
contribute to spreading the knowledge on the little things that I do know.
Hope my readers agree.</p>

<p>Stay tuned for some posts soon. I will be writing quite a bit about OpenSwitch,
but also random thoughts on different areas about Open + Network.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
