<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Open Source | The Open Network Geek Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://opennetgeek.github.io/blog/categories/open-source/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://opennetgeek.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-26T04:07:54-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://opennetgeek.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Diego Dompe]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenSwitch Containers ♥ GNS3]]></title>
    <link href="http://opennetgeek.github.io/blog/2016/06/25/openswitch-containers-gns3/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-25T23:09:46-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://opennetgeek.github.io/blog/2016/06/25/openswitch-containers-gns3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/OpenSwitchDocker.png" title="&lsquo;OpenSwitchDocker&rsquo; &lsquo;OpenSwitchDocker&rsquo;" ></p>

<p><div class="toc"/></p>

<p>In one of my <a href="http://opennetgeek.github.io/blog/2016/05/05/setting-up-dc-fabric-simulation-with-openswitch-and-gns3/">previous articles</a>,
I elaborated on a setup to create DC fabric simulations with GNS3 and OpenSwitch.
I also promised to follow up with some post about using Ansible with it.</p>

<p>Well, I have been a bit distracted with some changes to the setup before moving into
the Ansible details (to say true, I got the Ansible article almost ready, but things
are moving so fast, that I keep rewriting it).</p>

<p>One of the things that &lsquo;change everything&rsquo; recently was the
<a href="https://www.gns3.com/news/article/what-s-new-in-gns3-v1-5">release of GNS3 1.5</a>.
This is a great release that includes several features that makes using OpenSwitch with GNS3 awesome:</p>

<ul>
<li>Support for Docker containers! This enables OpenSwitch to be a container instead of
a VM, allowing to scale better:

<ul>
<li>This obviously consumes less RAM memory and use it more efficiently.</li>
<li>We are no longer limited to 8 ports per node (VirtualBox&rsquo;s restriction), but
instead we can have as many ports as you want. Even more, the OpenSwitch Appliance
container will change the number of ports available, based on the GNS3 configuration.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Support for portable projects! Now you can export your project and shared it
with others (restrictions apply).</li>
</ul>


<p>Let&rsquo;s see how to use this new release with OpenSwitch Appliance Container.</p>

<p><!--more--></p>

<h1>Using the GNS3 VM</h1>

<p>The first recommendation when using the container setup for GNS3, is to use the
GNS3 VM (even when using a native Linux host). Why?</p>

<ul>
<li>Well, for running containers on Linux or Windows, you need the GNS3 VM.
<div class="callout bottom-left">
Yeah, even if you have docker for Linux/Windows, GNS3 can create the virtual interfaces
for them on these platforms.
</div></li>
<li>Right now the only way to create a portable way to connect to the external world is to
use the <a href="https://www.gns3.com/marketplace/appliance/internet-for-gns3vm">GNS3 Internet VM Appliance</a>,
and this only works inside the GNS3 VM.</li>
<li>With GNS3 1.5, you can setup a remote GNS3 VM machine, allowing to deploy
a powerful VM for running your simulations without starving your laptop.</li>
<li>Also with the GNS3 VM, there is a simplified process for setting up a proxy when
working in a corporate environment.</li>
</ul>


<p>Since we will be using qemu appliances inside the GNS3 VM, you need a virtualization
platform that supports nested virtualization. That means you are either using a
VMware desktop solution (Workstation, Player or Fusion), or if using ESXi, be sure
to <a href="http://www.virtuallyghetto.com/2012/08/how-to-enable-nested-esxi-other.html">enable the VHV flag</a>.</p>

<h2>Installing the GNS3 VM</h2>

<p>Download the VM <a href="https://github.com/GNS3/gns3-gui/releases">from here</a>. Be sure to download the
right image for either desktop solution or ESXi.</p>

<p>You will need at least version 1.5.0, but if you are behind a corporate firewall, you will need version
1.5.1 that <a href="https://github.com/GNS3/gns3-vm/issues/75">fixes a bug when configuring the proxy settings</a>.</p>

<p>After downloading the GNS3 VM appliance, import it into your virtualization solution, and reconfigure
with this minimal hardware requirements:</p>

<ul>
<li>512MB of RAM for every OpenSwitch container that you plan to run. For our examples 6GB of RAM should be enough.</li>
<li>2 CPU cores. If you can afford more, the better.</li>
</ul>


<p>If you are behind a corporate firewall, be sure to turn on the VM, and using the menu displayed when the VM boots,
configure the proxy settings.</p>

<p><img class="center no-border" src="/images/gns3containers/proxy.png"></p>

<h2>Configure GNS3 to use the VM</h2>

<p>If you haven&rsquo;t already, install GNS3 downloading <a href="https://github.com/GNS3/gns3-gui/releases">from here</a>
(be sure to use the same version as the VM image that you downloaded).</p>

<p>When configuring GNS3, the wizard doesn&rsquo;t allow you to configure a remote server GNS3 VM, but
you can abort the wizard, and add it later from the preferences panel (the IP address of
the VM is show on the information page displayed by the VM on boot, or available from the
text menu on the VM as well).</p>

<p><div class="callout bottom-left">
I found that when working behind a proxy, the VM only works well as a remote server,
since somehow the communication with it cannot be established by the UI in the presense
of a proxy (I have only experienced this with <strike>OS-X</strike>macOS environment, not sure if
happens on Windows or Linux).
</div></p>

<p><img class="center no-border" src="/images/gns3containers/gns3vm-preferences.png"></p>

<h1>Using the OpenSwitch Docker Appliance with GNS3</h1>

<p>In order to use OpenSwitch as a container with GNS3, you have to main options:
use an existing image (easier one), or build a custom one from scratch (useful for developers).</p>

<h2>Using an Existing OpenSwitch Container Image</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s focus on the simple procedure first. Fortunately we no longer need to specify multiple
parameters on the UI to create a template, since for Docker containers we can use
a pre-defined template appliance (.gns3a file), that will do all the configuration
for you.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>First, download a GNS3 appliance template from the list
<a href="https://archive.openswitch.net/gns3/">available here</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Next, import it into GNS3: there is a new &lsquo;Import appliance template&rsquo; button under
the device panel.</p>

<p><img class="center no-border" src="/images/gns3containers/import1.png"></p>

<p>Select &lsquo;Import an appliance template file&rsquo;</p>

<p><img class="center no-border" src="/images/gns3containers/import2.png"></p>

<p>Select the template that you downloaded, and follow the rest of the wizard. Select
to run on the remote server running the GNS3 VM.</p>

<p><img class="center no-border" src="/images/gns3containers/import3.png"></p></li>
</ul>


<p><img class="img-right-callout <a" src="href="https://archive.openswitch.net/logo/OpenSwitchDockerStencil.png">https://archive.openswitch.net/logo/OpenSwitchDockerStencil.png</a>"></p>

<p>Once you are done with the import, you can download a custom stencil for OpenSwitch
Docker Appliance <a href="https://archive.openswitch.net/logo/OpenSwitchDockerStencil.png">from here</a>,
and customize the template to use it.</p>

<p>The template uses by default 8 ports, but that can be adjusted in per machine instance.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s all it takes, you are ready to drag &amp; drop container instances into GNS3!</p>

<h2>Creating a custom Container Image</h2>

<p>In the previous step where we used the .gns3a file, it points to a published version
of the container in the Docker Hub, but you may want to create your own container from
scratch with the latest code or modifications. If that is not the case, you can skip
this section.</p>

<p>First you will have to build an image for the appliance target as explained in
previous articles (you can also download the tarball for a periodic build from
the <a href="https://archive.openswitch.net/artifacts">artifact archives</a>).</p>

<p><div class="callout bottom-left">
An important clarification: if you are a developer from OpenSwitch, you may be used
to know the &lsquo;genericx86-64&rsquo; target as the container image used for testing purposes. However
on GNS3, we actually use the OpenSwitch Appliance images. This have implications on the
naming of the ports (ports are called ethX).
</div></p>

<p>Now, the default tarball created for the appliance is designed to run in a VM, so
it needs some small modifications to run properly on a container. I have automated
the steps in a <a href="https://github.com/ddompe/ops-gns3-docker/blob/master/openswitch/Dockerfile">docker file here</a>.</p>

<p>Here are the example commands to create a custom image with the latest code from
master and push into the docker hub (in this example I use my docker hub account):
<code>
mkdir ops-gns3-docker
curl https://archive.openswitch.net/artifacts/periodic/master/latest/appliance/openswitch-appliance-image-appliance-ops-0.4.0-master+2016063012.tar.gz &gt; openswitch-appliance-image.tar.gz
wget https://raw.githubusercontent.com/ddompe/ops-gns3-docker/master/openswitch/Dockerfile
docker build -t ddompe/openswitch-appliance:latest .
docker login
docker push ddompe/openswitch-appliance:latest
</code></p>

<p>Now you can modify the gns3a file provided in the previous step and point to your
customized image to import it into GNS3.</p>

<h1>Creating a topology for Ansible experimentation</h1>

<p>Now, let&rsquo;s create a topology for creating a DC Fabric simulation with Ansible similar
to the one described in the <a href="http://opennetgeek.github.io/blog/2016/05/05/setting-up-dc-fabric-simulation-with-openswitch-and-gns3/">previous article using virtual machine appliances</a>.</p>

<p>I have created a docker container that already automated all the steps detailed in
the previous article, and is suitable to be run as a systemd container. The Dockerfile
could be found <a href="https://github.com/ddompe/ops-gns3-docker/tree/master/dc-controller">here</a>, and
the GNS3 template file <a href="https://archive.openswitch.net/gns3/ansible-controller.gns3a">here</a>.</p>

<p>Unlike the previous examples using VirtualBox, we cannot longer use the cloud element
to get a NAT connection to the external world, so instead we will use the
<a href="https://www.gns3.com/marketplace/appliance/internet-for-gns3vm">GNS3 Internet VM Appliance</a>.</p>

<p>After installing those two templates, we can recreate the DC fabric similar to the one
from the previous article, with the difference that is (almost) all containers.</p>

<p><img class="center no-border" src="/images/gns3containers/topology.png"></p>

<h1>Sharing portable projects</h1>

<p>Now comes another cool part, you can export and import the project to share with
others.
<div class="callout bottom-left">
Yes, that means you can ignore everything I just said about importing templates
and drawing topologies and just download a file with everything ready.
I know I could have started saying this, but where is the fun if not in do it by
yourself?
</div></p>

<p>So, you can export the project by using &lsquo;Export portable project&rsquo; on the file
menu. It will ask you if you wan to include any base image, which for our example
I would recommend we do (this will pack the qemu image used by the GNS3 Internet Appliance).
Docker images won&rsquo;t get included on the file, but instead will be automatically
downloaded from the docker hub when someone imports the project.</p>

<p>Talking about importing the project back, there is currently a <a href="https://github.com/GNS3/gns3-gui/issues/1336">bug when importing
the project and downloading the docker images</a>,
where certain imports may timeout. This is fixed for 1.5.1, but in the meantime you can workaround by deleting the
project that failed to import and re-import it again (since the docker images should
be already downloaded, it won&rsquo;t fail the second time).</p>

<p>The portable project file for the example on this article is
<a href="https://archive.openswitch.net/gns3/dc-fabric-example.gns3project">here</a>, in case you
want to get up an running.</p>

<h1>Next Steps</h1>

<p>Isn&rsquo;t all of this really exciting? Thanks to the GNS3 team for their awesome work
and their responsiveness to fix the bug/enhancements that I keep throwing at them.</p>

<p>In the next article I will continue with explaining how to use Ansible to deploy
configuration to the topology we build here.</p>

<p>Stay tuned.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Starting a Blog on Open Software/Hardware + Networking]]></title>
    <link href="http://opennetgeek.github.io/blog/2016/03/22/starting-a-blog-on-open-software-slash-hardware-plus-networking/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-22T14:51:39-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://opennetgeek.github.io/blog/2016/03/22/starting-a-blog-on-open-software-slash-hardware-plus-networking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I’m jumping into water to start writing about some area where I have some
half-decent background: the intersection of Open Software/Hardware and Networking.</p>

<h2>Why?</h2>

<p>You see, I’m a software guy. The pragmatical Linux/OpenSource fanboy kind. What
that means? I have a formal degree on Computer Science, and wrote Linux drivers
and software for embedded systems for 8 years. But I’m also a pragmatical guy:
I know how to write kernel drivers, but I use a Mac laptop every day because
I like things to work. For the last 4 years I have been learning a big from
networking at Hewlett Packard Enterprise, where I have worked on networking
(SDN, ASICs), and more recently on the OpenSwitch project.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Why start writing about the intersection of Open and Networking? These are
interesting times in the networking world: disaggregation, open source,
open hardware, etc. All of this is pretty new for the networking world, and is
specially different because in the old good days you will have limited
information about the technical details of what is going on behind scenes on
your network. Now sharing the knowledge is critical. I have been inspired by
reading blog entries from many in the networking community, and I’m by no
means close to have the expertise of guys like Ivan or Greg, but I think I can
contribute to spreading the knowledge on the little things that I do know.
Hope my readers agree.</p>

<p>Stay tuned for some posts soon. I will be writing quite a bit about OpenSwitch,
but also random thoughts on different areas about Open + Network.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
